[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have a problem keeping myself busy within the precepts, but when I reflect on the value of those precepts, the weight of my situation and of that commitment becomes very heavy, and becoming overwhelmed, I stop with that reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: What should I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the training is happening while you're doing that reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, while your mind feels confined by thinking about permanently keeping the precepts, that's when you're actually training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, breaking the precepts will lead you to not just not do the training, but actively go in the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start getting overwhelmed, sure, stop reflecting on that, but don't break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you pause the training, but you don't start training the opposite thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, whenever that kind of overly, you know, excessive pressure calms down, you will be able to continue the same reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference between keeping the precepts as an external thing that you just happen not to be doing, while your mind is going left and right,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes even contemplating breaking the precepts, and keeping the precepts while that internal boundary is firmly established, which exactly will result in that, like a sense of confinement, and a sense of... like actually having to give up those possibilities, versus just, oh, I'm not doing it right now, which is no different than a normal person.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, they spend 90% of their time probably not breaking the precepts,
[SPEAKER_00]: But they never have to confront the internal recognition of, I will not be able to do this again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, they would only have to grapple with that if some external thing prevents them from breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it's like, even if something external prevents them, they would still be hoping for the day where they can regain that possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like when you get sick, you're still anticipating, even if you can't, you know, pursue sensuality right now, you're still hoping for the the day where you'll be able to go back to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the precepts will only be kept when that door is completely closed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's something that you internally have to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to happen by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind will still maintain those hopes to return to what has been given up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why in the suttas, the Buddha would say, the accomplishment in virtue is when the mind becomes like a king who has defeated all of his enemies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, sees no danger in any direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the sense that now... See, you don't need to have an explicit plan that on such and such a day, on such and such a time, I will give in to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you're not sure, that you will never do it, means the mind is not established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, establishing yourself in virtue doesn't mean you know exactly what you're going to do in advance.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what you can know for sure is, what am I intending not to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you intend not to break the precepts, and you see that there is no inclination to do so either, then you can be sure that that action will not happen, regardless of what the future holds.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a certainty that you gain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You factually have no idea what will happen tomorrow, but you know that this will not be one of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I'm intending not to do it, and also there is no craving to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if your mind starts craving to do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's exactly the... like, that craving is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, number one, you have been breaking the precepts, and number two, you have been allowing the possibility of breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't need to... like, imagine, factually, like an animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to let it go to where it wants to go, in order for it to be agitated.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to allow the hope.
[SPEAKER_00]: That it will be able to go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the hope is allowed automatically by you not closing the door.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those actions are pretty much the path of least resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're the the the pasture of your existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, just by not being free from sensuality, not being free from ill will,
[SPEAKER_00]: Those actions are floating around in your field of view, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't determine not to do them, you don't close the door to go towards them, destroy the bridge, as the Buddha called it, then your... the intention to do them lingers, even vaguely, and that's what keeps the mind craving to do them.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it... when all the hope is taken away, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you reflected on the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reflected on how it's factually better not to do those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that's how the craving will disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not a... it's not a matter of you doing that once.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's maintaining that confinement up until, for long enough, the door has been closed and the hope fades to ever go through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do you only do the training when the dog is already agitated?
[SPEAKER_01]: You just wait until it's agitated, and then you... that's when you start teaching it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you close the door?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the time you leave it open?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Essentially, that is what the right mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like those similes the Buddha gave, where you would keep like a bowl... you would avoid spilling even a drop of the bowl of oil that you're carrying on your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not just that the animal has to be agitated, the mind has to be agitated for you to need to do those reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said, your state of being implies those actions, because it's still the central being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you not being clear that you will not do them,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're not actively planning to do them, already means you're not... you're... you're allowing the craving to survive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to live throughout your day with the context that this will not be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Explicitly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to maintain that perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, if not breaking precepts is... externally was... would automatically purify your mind, and all you would have to do is get some kind of disease that makes you immobile, and then you wouldn't be... you would become an arhant eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because internally, you're still, again, allowing that door, leaving that door open.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actually what even monks would often not want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, you spend 20 years in robes, and even if you die in robes, you never actually closed off the chance that you could return to sensuality eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, unless you have the right perspective, that craving has to be given up, because it's the root of suffering, you won't be able to have right intention, which is intention of renunciation, unconditional renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, because you don't see the danger, because you're covering it up or not even trying to reflect on it, you won't be able to establish that unconditional resolve, because you're still in doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That these actions are categorically unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to clarify that first.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to understand, why am I keeping these precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I restraining myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to arrive at some, you know, super correct theoretical answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you can find different aspects of what kind of reflects that danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: What drawbacks you can recognize from engaging in craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you make sure that that is clear, and that as a result of that, you keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you'll be actually, by keeping the precepts, you'll be wearing away the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like that simile the Buddha gave, where you have a fire that's burning with cartloads and cartloads of wood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you don't need to want for the fire to continue.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is keep throwing fuel at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you throw the fuel in the most obvious way, by breaking the precepts, and then, in the less obvious way, by not being certain that you won't break them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said, that keeps the door open.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you contemplate the danger, and automatically, that is what closes the door, because you wouldn't want to engage in something that is categorically against your welfare.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do you wear the precepts, like how they can describe the satipaṭṭhāna, like a jacket?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you wear the precepts and that wears away the cravings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you have to... as the suttas describe, you abide diligent, ardent and resolute.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not just like floating around in limbo.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep that in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not even something that... like you're not keeping the precepts harder by remembering that you won't break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you not do something harder?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about adding to the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about demolishing the bridge that you're already not crossing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just keeping that recognition of this will not be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like a... well, like another simile the Buddha gave, like a hot pan, where all the drops would fall, that would fall, would immediately just evaporate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like any little intention, doesn't matter how fleeting it is, to... to like... ah, maybe... it will dissipate, because the door is completely closed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will never be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of chasing after the... the little intentions that you might think you need to... to... to pick out individually,
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, like, oh, all of those intentions, they can only exist if this specific action is not completely abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why would you be thinking about what you're going to eat if there's no food in the fridge?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you... if... only if you forgot the fact that there is no food, would it make any sense for you to start thinking about what you're going to eat?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you think about what color you're going to paint your room if you have no room?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like people would be generally trying to chase after like, oh, this intention that came up and I didn't see it or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, that's endless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to sneak in from whichever direction, as long as you're not clear about that specific thing that will not be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's all leaning in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: These intentions towards sensuality cannot be isolated.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're always pointing towards a specific action.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be having sensual desire to, I don't know, touch a tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's always...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it can arise through different things, through subtler things, but it's always because that specific thing is not being clarified as abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these little other things are kind of steps, slowly leading in that direction, that again, would not be happening if you were to be clear about that specific thing being out of bounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speaking out of lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why would you have any interest in having harmless little conversations with somebody you're attracted to, if you were to not forget that you're celibate forever?
[SPEAKER_00]: Any conversation you would have would not be lustful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if it was happening, it would be for some other reason than lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only when... See, again, you're not necessarily planning towards intercourse or towards any kind of unwholesome action.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just not being clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: This will not be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaving it ambiguous makes the lust able to land.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, even if you don't do anything at the end.